NYSUT Convention files 6174/010
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
NYSUT Convention files
1959-2005
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
New York State United Teachers (NYSUT)
6174/010
6 cubic feet
6 linear ft.
Reports, pamphlets, correspondence, publications.
5830502
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, June 18, 2012
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, October 31, 2013
Biographical / Historical
New York State United Teachers (NYSUT) was created in 1972 by the merger of the New York State Teachers Association (NYSTA) and the United Teachers of New York (UTNY). NYSTA had been affiliated with the National Education Association (NEA), and UTNY with the American Federation of Teachers (AFT). UTNY was the statewide organization whose United Federation of Teachers (UFT), led by Albert Shanker, was the predominant teachers' union in New York City. In joining with United Teachers and affiliating with the AFT, NYSUT also became a member union of the AFL-CIO.
In 1976, NYSUT voted to disaffiliate with the NEA. Some locals left NYSUT and created the NYEA (New York Educators Association), which became the state affiliate for the NEA. In the early 1980s, NYEA changed its name to NEA-NY.
NYEA/NEA- NY viewed association with the AFL-CIO's industrial unions as undermining the professional image and independence of teachers. The two organizations also differed strongly on aspects of the governance structure, particularly with respect to ethnic minority representation, with NYSUT opposed to mandatory minimums. The rivalry between NYSUT and NYEA/NEA-NY in organizing new locals expended a great deal of resources for both labor organizations.
While competition with NYEA/NEA-NY was a constant focus of NYSUT's organizing efforts for teachers, NYSUT was also organizing college faculty members, nurses, and other non-teaching personnel. Once members were organized, NYSUT continued to advocate for teachers' and other workers' rights through contract support and legal services at the local level and political involvement at the state and federal levels, supporting candidates and legislation that protected funding, due process, and working conditions.
NEA-N Y merged with NYSUT in 2006, by which time NYSUT had grown to more than half a million members, becoming the largest union in New York State.
Scope and Contents
Covers 1970-1999, with some material dating back to 1959. Materials for NYSUT/NYSTA Representative Assembly/Delegate Assembly, the annual convention of the New York State teachers union.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 6174/013 AV: New York State United Teachers (NYSUT). Representative Assembly (RA). Audio-visual materials. All other 6174 collections
Teachers' unions -- New York (State); New York State United Teachers; New York State United Teachers, Representative Assembly
5830502
- NYSUT Delegate Lists, 1973-1982 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Delegate lists and committee assignments for Representative Assembly
- NYSUT Representative Assembly (RA) (1 of 2), 1982 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Delegate list and committee assignments; legislative program; proposed resolutions and amendments; budget report; paper by NYSUT general counsel Bernard Ashe, "Recent Cases Affecting Teacher Employment in the State of New York"; NYSUT constitution as amended by the 1981 Representative Assembly; document, "Extremist Groups in the United States: A Curriculum Guide for Secondary Schools," by the Anti-Defamation League of B'nai B'rith, with cover letter to delegates from NYSUT president Tom Hobart; computer printout of NYSUT membership, "Final Entitlement Report 1982"; mailing packet of RA materials
- NYSUT RA (2 of 2), 1982 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Individual nametags; individual registration forms
- NYSUT RA (1 of 2), 1981 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Computer printout of committee assignments; booklet, Delegate List and Committee Assignments; proposed resolutions and amendments; budget report; legislative program; 1981 Representative Assembly Questions and Answers on the Proposed Dues Increase; NYSUT constitution as amended by the 1980 Representative Assembly; mailing packet
- NYSUT RA (2 of 2), 1981 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Computer printout, final Representative Assembly Entitlement Report; individual registration forms; alternate authorization cards
- NYSUT RA, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  Program; computer printout of delegates, alternates, and committee assignments; booklet, List of Delegates and Committee Assignments; text of president's address; NYSUT constitution as amended through April 29, 1979; brochure, "The Levittown Decision: Where It Stands"; poster re NYSUT accomplishments; NYSUT In the News (compilation of newspaper clippings by public relations office); proposed resolutions and constitutional amendments; budget report; legislative program; NYSUT pin and key ring; plastic portfolio
- NYSUT RA (1 of 2), 1979 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  Computer printouts of delegates and alternates; alternate authorization cards; minutes of meetings of Credential Committee, 1977 and 1978; Credentials Committee procedures (proposed policy motions); other materials
- NYSUT R/A (2 of 2), 1979 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  Computer printout of roll call re dues increase; text of president's address; report on resolutions considered at 1979 Representative Assembly, with cover letter from NYSUT president Tom Hobart; memo re attendance by Gov. Hugh Carey and other elected officials, March 26; proposed resolutions and constitutional amendments; program; report on implementation of 1978 resolutions; budget report; list of representatives and committee assignments; legislative program; major legislative gains, '74-'78; constitution as amended through April 9, 1978; booklet, "Tenure-What It Means to You"
- NYSUT RA (1 of 2), 1978 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  Program; resolutions and proposed constitutional amendments; report on implementation of 1977 resolutions; budget report; list of representatives and committee assignments; legislative program; constitution as amended through March 27, 1977; first mailing packet, with conference call and list of affiliated local units; computer printout of 1978 entitlement; Special Report to the 1978 Representative Assembly from the Committee to Study the Position of Director-at-Large; correspondence; materials re credentials committee, rules of order; VOTE/COPE (political action committee) poster and brochure; samples of official badges; plastic portfolio
- NYSUT RA (2 of 2), 1978 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  Reports of resolutions committees; minutes of credentials committee, 1976 and 1977; computer printout of committee assignments; NYSUT 1978 election results; list of agency fee locals as of February 1978; list of disaffiliated locals as of November 1, 1977; list of locals in arrears as of March 31, 1978; letters to presidents of locals in arrears; thank-you letters to members of the credentials committee; memo noting that NYSUT Board of Directors had determined that 50 was a major fraction of 100, politically if not mathematically
- Meeting-NYC-New York Hilton, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  Program; resolutions and proposed constitutional amendments; legislative program; list of representatives and committee assignments; report on implementation of 1977 resolutions; samples of official badges; conference call; proposed rules of order; memo re delegate entitlement and voting strength for 1978 Representative Assembly; list of minority locals as of March 22, 1977; lists of sergeant-at-arms and teller responsibilities; staffing assignments; mailing packets to field reps; press release, "Top Political, Educational and Labor Leaders to Address Teacher Union Convention," March 31
- NYSUT RA, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  Computer printouts of representatives (delegates) and alternates, local presidents; NYSUT Update newsletter, announcing special endorsement meeting for governor, September 29, 1978; related memos and press release; information compiled by NYSUT Legislative Department re voting records of Gov. Hugh Carey (D) and candidate Perry Duryea, Republican Assembly Minority Leader
- West Hempstead Maintenance ASSP, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  Identification cards for delegates and local presidents to special meeting, October 9, 1978; rules and procedures for special meeting
- West Hempstead Office Staff ASSP, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  Visitor passes; resolution recommending Carey endorsement; list of NYS congressional candidates and candidates for state Senate and Assembly, indicting endorsements by NYSUT
- Convention Call, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  NYSUT Who's Who and Delegate List; NYSUT 1988 Annual Report: Meeting the Challenge of Education Reform; legislative program; implementation of actions by the 1987 Representative Assembly; Report of the Commissioner's Task Force on the Teaching Profession: The New York Report: A Blueprint for Learning and Teaching; NYSUT constitution as amended through the 1987 Representative Assembly; budget summary; NYSUT Award Recipients; memos to local presidents; brochures re benefits; pen
- Convention Call, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  April 13-15. NYSUT constitution; legislative program; conventional call; program; budget summary; newsletters; question and answer sheet re dues increase
- Convention Call, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  March 22-25. Convention call; facilitative correspondence
- RA Delegate Kit, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  March 22-25. Program; proposed resolutions and amendments; questions and answers on proposed constitutional amendment #4; budget summary; 1990 annual report; legislative program; report on legislation passed (Focus on "K-12 1989"); brochures on academic freedom, Eastern Airlines strike
- Convention Call, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  Convention call, "Education: A National Priority"; NYSUT constitution, March 1990; implementation of actions by the 1990 Representative Assembly
- RA Delegate Kit, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  March 21-24. Program; NYSUT constitution, March 1990; budget summary; questions and answers re NYSUT dues; NYSUT publication, Indoor Air Pollution; "Multiple Choice: Reforming Student Testing in New York State," a report of the NYSUT Task Force on Student Assessment; legislative program; Who's Who (delegate list)
- Convention Call, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  Convention call; NYSUT constitution; announcement for journalism competition
- Convention Call, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- RA Delegate Kit, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  NYSUT 1993 Legislative Program; proposed resolutions and constitutional amendments; NYSUT constitution, March 1991; budget summary; checklist of NYSUT services; member benefits progress report; NYSUT tie tack, pen, and badge holder
- Convention Call, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  Conventional call; facilitative correspondence; list of officer and delegate positions to be filled
- RA Delegate Kit, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  Program; proposed resolutions and constitutional amendments; 1994 legislative program; NYSUT constitution, May 1993; 1993 VOTE/COPE Awards; member benefits yearly report; budget summary; local assessment of NYSUT services
- Convention Call, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  Call for nominations for SRP (school-related personnel) Employee of the Year; announcement for Pre- Representative Assembly Local Presidents' Conference; convention call, with facilitative material
- RA Delegate Kit, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  Program; daily summaries of the proceedings; list of Republican senators and points to include in letters; Report of the Resolutions Committees; 1995 legislative program; budget summary; map of NYSUT election districts and list of Board of Directors; Rules of Procedure and Proposed Resolutions; VOTE/COPE Awards; member benefits yearly report; NYSUT license plate frame
- Convention Call, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  Convention call; nomination form for SRP Employee of the Year; list of positions to be filled, with election procedures; announcement for Pre-Representative Assembly Local Presidents' Conference; NYSUT constitution, May 1993
- RA Delegate Kit, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  Proposed Constitutional Amendments and Resolutions; 1995 Final Legislative Report; 1996 Legislative Program; VOTE/COPE Awards; member benefits yearly report; brochure, "Dollars and Sense: Responding to Attacks on Teachers' Salaries: A Guide for Local Leaders"; brochure for NYSUT Distinguished Service Award; NYSUT tie tack, pen, Lessons for Life button
- Convention Call, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  Conventional Call; announcement for Pre-Representative Assembly Local Presidents' Conference; nomination form for SRP Employee of the Year; NYSUT Constitution, May 1993
- RA Delegate Kit, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  Proposed constitutional amendments and resolutions; 1997 Legislative Program; budget summary; photos of NYSUT Board of Directors 1996; NYSUT constitution, May 1993; annual report to NYSUT delegates; Lessons for Life tie tack, pen, badge holder
- Convention Call, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  Convention Call; announcement for Pre-Representative Assembly Local Presidents' Conference; NYSUT constitution, effective May 1997; list of positions to be filled
- RA Delegate Kit, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  Program; Report and Recommendations of the Task Force to Increase Participation of School Related Personnel in NYSUT; 1998 Community Service Awards; NYSUT Ad Hoc Task Force on the Needs of Rural Locals Final Report, February 1988; Local Assessment of NYSUT Services 1997-98: Report to the 1998 Representative Assembly; 1997 VOTE/COPE Awards; Annual Report to NYSUT Delegates from Walter S. Dunn, Jr., NYSUT second vice president, May 1998; 1998 Legislative Program; Budget Summary; Proposed Constitutional Amendments and Resolutions; NYSUT Constitution, effective May 1997; memorabilia
- Convention Call, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  Convention Call; announcement for Pre-Representative Assembly Local Presidents' Conference; travel brochures for Niagara Falls, Canada
- RA Delegate Kit, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  Program; Proposed Constitutional Amendments and Resolutions; 1999 NYSUT Community Service Awards; NYSUT Constitution effective May 1998; Budget Summary 1998-99; 1999 Legislative Program; 1998 Final Legislative Report; 1998 VOTE/COPE Awards; Annual Report to the NYSUT Delegates from Walter E. Dunn, Jr., NYSUT second vice president; list and photos of regional office coordinators and legal staff
- Landrum Griffin Act, 1973-1986 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  Text of relevant provisions; legal memoranda from NYSUT counsel to NYSUT president Tom Hobart; memo from Terry Herndon, executive director of NEA, re applicability of Landrum-Griffin, February 23, 1979; publication by U.S. Department of Labor, "Electing Union Officers," revised 1980; AFL-CIO booklet, "How to Run a Union Meeting," revised December 1980; AFT brochure, "How to Conduct Democratic Union Elections," November 1978; related correspondence
- Landrum Griffin, 1959-1986 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  Landrum-Griffin checklist; publication by U.S. Department of Labor, "Electing Union Officers," revised 1980; text of Labor-Management Reporting and Disclosure Act of 1959, as amended, March 1977; related brochures and bulletins; conference call for fourth annual Representative Assembly, March 4-7, 1976; NYSUT Election Guidelines and Information, 1974; NYSUT Constitution, as amended by the 1981 Representative Assembly; memo, "NYSUT Policy Regarding Local Elections," January 21, 1982; document, "NYSUT Locals and Landrum-Griffin," summarizing provisions with which locals must comply
- Delegate List (1 of 5), 1972-1999 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  Computer printouts
- Delegate List (2 of 5), 1972-1999 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  Computer printouts and Who's Who list
- Delegate List (3 of 5), 1972-1999 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  Computer printouts, Who's Who list, and list of delegates and committee assignments
- Delegate List (4 of 5), 1972-1999 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  Lists of delegates and committee assignments
- Delegate List (5 of 5), 1972-1979 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  Lists of representatives (delegates)
- New York Teacher, 1978-2005 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  Original issues for Representative Assembly
- New York Teacher, 1978-2005 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- New York Teacher, 1978-2005 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Weighted Voting, 1970-1986 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  Lists of Board of Directors and others
- RA Evaluation, 1991-1999 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  Blank evaluation forms for delegate feedback re Representative Assembly
- Representative Assembly, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  Booklet re first Representative Assembly of merged teacher's organization, prepared for media; list of media representatives attending; conference call; nominating petition for officers; candidates' statements, printed in New York Teacher; proposed order of business; list of NYSUT E.D. directors; form thank-you letter from Tom Hobart and Al Shanker
- Election Assembly, 1996-1998 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  Computer printout of 1996 election results for officers, by E.D.; list of vote totals for officers, 1996 and 1998; 1998 election results printed in New York Teacher
- Representative Assembly-Originals for Duplicating, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  Ballot forms for various Election Districts; list of interim E.D. chairmen; list of additions to Resolutions Committees
- UTNY Membership and Delegates Entitlement RA, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  Press release, "NYSUT Convention Moved to Montreal," March 12, 1973; tentative program; list of NYSUT paid membership as of January 31, 1973; list of UTNY locals
- Representative Assembly-Misc. Material, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  Press release, "AFT President Condemns Nixon 'Ice Age' at New York Teacher Meeting," March 24, 1973; letter to delegates from NYSUT co-presidents Tom Hobart and Al Shanker that the venue for the newly merged union's Representative Assembly was moving from the Concord Hotel in upstate New York to the Queen Elizabeth Hotel in Montreal, Canada, due to labor difficulties, March 9, 1973; letters of protest at change of venue, calling it unpatriotic; list of representatives (delegates); correspondence; conference call; proposed order of business
- Evaluations Recap, 1990-1999 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  Summaries of evaluations
- Representative Assembly, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  Implementation of Actions by the 1992 Representative Assembly; Proposed Resolutions, 20th Annual Representative Assembly, March 19-21, 1992; legal memorandum from NYSUT counsel Bernard Ashe re special order of business, June 29, 1992; memo re assignment of adopted resolutions from 1992 RA to committees for implementation; Report of the Resolutions Committees for 1992 RA; Proposed Resolutions and Constitutional Amendments, 19th annual Representative Assembly, March 21-24, 1991; Implementation of Actions by the 1991 Representative Assembly; Reports of the Resolutions Committees, March 21-24, 1991; Proposed Resolutions and Amendments, 1990 Representative Assembly; Implementation of Actions by the 1990 Representative Assembly; memo re assignment of resolutions adopted by 1990 RA
- Bylaw Proposals (NYSTA), 1970-1971 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  Report of the Resolutions Committee to House of Delegates, New York State Teachers Association (NYSTA), November 7, 1971; 1971 Resolutions; NYSTA constitution and bylaws; memo re proposed bylaw changes; related correspondence
- NYSUT Constitution Amendments, 1993-1998 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  Rules of Procedure and Proposed Resolutions for 23rd annual RA, 1995, 22nd RA, 1994, and 24th RA, 1993; Implementation of Actions by the 1993, 1994, and 1998 Representative Assembly; Report of the Resolutions Committees, 1993; Report of the Constitutional Amendments Committee, 1994; Proposed Constitutional Amendments and Resolutions, 1996 and 1997; special orders of business, 1994, 1995, 1996, and 1997
- Representative Handbooks, 1965-1973 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  Delegate handbooks
- NYSUT Proposed Constitution Amendments, 1973-1977 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  Proposed constitutional amendments and resolutions, presented at Representative Assemblies
- NYSUT Proposed Constitution Amendments, 1978-1982 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- NYSUT Proposed Constitution Amendments, 1983-1987 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  Proposed constitutional amendments and resolutions, presented at Representative Assemblies; implementation of actions
- Convention Call Wrapper, 1979-1998 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  Convention calls for Representative Assemblies
- Campaign and Election Procedure, 1992-1998 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  Flyers re NYSUT officer positions to be filled
- RA Programs, 1973-1978 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  Programs for Representative Assemblies
- Community Service Award Winners, 1993-1998 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  Programs for awards, describing local winners
- NYSUT Constitutions, 1985-1999 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  Printed constitutions
- Proposed Constitutional Amendments and Resolutions and Implementation of Actions, 1995-1999 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  Printed materials for Representative Assemblies
- Proposed Constitutional Amendments and Resolutions and Implementation of Actions, 1990-1994 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Proposed Constitutional Amendments and Resolutions and Implementation of Actions, 1988-1989 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Implementation of Actions, 1985-1989 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  Materials for Representative Assemblies
- Amendments to NYSUT Bylaws/Constitution, 1973-1989 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Amendments: House of Delegates, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  Proposed amendments to constitution and bylaws of the New York State Teachers Association (NYSTA)
- Report on Attendance, 1976-1999 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  Various lists of locals attending the Representative Assembly
- New York Teacher-Special RA editions, 1973-1977 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  Original newspapers